in this video we're going to talk about
rotational motion
so what exactly
is rotational motion
from the word you can describe that it's
any object that can rotate or spin
so that's rotational motion
it's different from linear motion where
an object simply moves forward
linear motion and translational motion
basically means the same thing
now so what terms do you need to be
familiar with
when dealing with rotational motion
well in linear motion you have things
like position and displacement
for instance
let's say if this is a number line
and
an object is currently at position a
so position is basically a point in
space
displacement is the change in position
let's say if the object moves from x8 to
xb
then the object's displacement is the
difference between
xb and x8
it's the final position
minus the initial position that's
displacement
well for rotational motion we have the
same terms
there's angular position and angular
displacement
so angular position
just like regular position is a point on
the circle let's call this point a
and let's say as the wheel spins
point
the object moves from point a
to let's say point b
so
this angle represents the angular
position
and this is also the angular position
but the difference between those two
points
i guess you can call it delta theta
this is the angular displacement
is the difference
between those two points in a circle
it's the final angular position
minus the initial angular position
so that's angular displacement
now the standard unit for angular
displacement
is the unit radians
now you can use degrees
or any type of angle measure but
the most common unit that you're going
to see is radiance
now the next term that you need to be
familiar with
is angular velocity
angular velocity tells you how fast an
object is spinning on a circle
whereas linear velocity tells you how
fast it's moving forward
so the average linear velocity
or let's say average
linear speed is distance divided by time
velocity is really displacement over
time
but the units will still be meters per
second
now
angular velocity which is represented by
the symbol omega
this is going to be average angular
velocity
it's equal to the angular displacement
divided by the time
and as you can see
the equations are very similar
so for
average velocity we have units such as
meters per second
and for average angular velocity it's
radians per second
so here this is going to be
displacement over time
to get velocity and to get angle
velocity its angular displacement over
time
now the equation that connects
linear velocity
to angular velocity is this equation
linear velocity is equal to
omega times r
so whenever you have
an object spinning
the angular speed is the same everywhere
on a circle
however the linear speed is not the same
so let me give you an example that will
illustrate this
so let's say this is the center of the
circle
and
this circle is spinning at 5 radians per
second
so let's say this is point a
and this is point b
let's move point b to this position
so which one has the greater angular
velocity
point a or point b
now because the wheel is spinning at one
angle speed
every point on this will
will travel at that same speed it's
going to rotate at that same rate
so the angular velocity of a
is equal to the angular velocity of
point b
they're going to rotate at the same rate
now what about the linear velocity is it
the same or is it different
now they all spin at the same rate but
point a
has a shorter distance to travel
point b has to travel a longer distance
and in order to spin at the same rate b
has to travel faster than a
so therefore the linear speed
of point b
is greater than the linear speed of
point a
and there's an equation that we can use
it's this one
v is equal to omega times r
so as r increases
the linear velocity will increase
so notice that
our a
is less
than rb
so that's one reason why
the linear velocity of b is greater than
the linear velocity of point a
now there's some other terms that you
need to know
and that is the period and the frequency
the period
is the time it takes to complete one
cycle
so if you have the total time and the
number of cycles that will make or
rotations if you divide these two
you're going to get the time it takes to
make one complete cycle
or
one full rotation around the circle
frequency
is the reciprocal of period
it's the number of cycles that occurs
per second
so if you have the number of cycles and
you divide it by the time
this will give you the frequency
so the unit for period is
the seconds but it's really seconds per
cycle or seconds per revolution
the unit frequency
is hertz or one over seconds
now period
is one divided by the frequency
can also calculate the angular velocity
if you know the frequency the angular
velocity is equal to 2 pi f
so this is one equation that you want to
commit to memory
and you also want to know this one as
well now if you have the period and you
want to calculate the angular speed
you can use this equation
omega is equal to two pi divided by t
so make sure you know those three
equations that can relate angular
velocity with period and frequency
now the next thing that we need to talk
about
is
angular acceleration and linear
acceleration
so linear acceleration
is the change in velocity
divided by the change in time
so this is average
linear acceleration
the average angular acceleration
is equal to a very similar equation it's
the change in angular velocity
divided by the change in time
the units for linear acceleration is
meters per second squared
for angle acceleration it's radians per
second squared
at least that's the standard unit
it's rare that you'll see degrees per
second squared but that would still be a
form of
angular acceleration but this is the
most common unit
now whenever you have an object moving
in circular motion there's different
types of accelerations that you need to
be familiar with
so
if the object has any kind of speed
if it's moving around a circle
it's going to have a centripetal
acceleration
and that centripetal acceleration
points towards the center of the circle
the centripetal acceleration is equal to
the linear speed squared divided by the
radius of the circle
and we know that v
is equal to omega r
so the centripetal acceleration is going
to be omega r
squared divided by r
so you can cancel one of the r's
so just to take it one step at a time
once you square omega r
you're going to have omega squared times
r squared which is r times r
and then you can cancel one of these so
the centripetal acceleration
is omega squared times r
so that's the acceleration that points
towards the center of the circle
so if an object is moving with constant
speed around a circle
the only
acceleration it has is the centripetal
acceleration also known as the radial
acceleration
so the net acceleration of the object
will equal ac
if it's moving with constant speed
now what if it's not moving with
constant speed what if it's accelerating
around a circle
so then it's going to have
a tangential acceleration
and the tangential acceleration
is equal to
the angular acceleration times r
and we also found the tangential
acceleration using this equation it's
the change in velocity divided by the
change in time
now notice that these two vectors
they're perpendicular to each other
so if we have the centripetal
acceleration
going this way
and this is the tangential acceleration
therefore the net acceleration of the
object
at
this instant
is going in the northwest direction
so when the object is not moving with
constant speed around a circle
the net acceleration
is the vector sum
of the centripetal acceleration and the
tangential acceleration
so basically it's the hypotenuse of the
right triangle
you